2018年2月6日 重型猎鹰遥一火箭将Starman和一辆特斯拉跑车送入太空
On the 6th of February 2018, the Falcon Heavy launched Starman and his Tesla Roadster into space.
离开地球后 Starman最终进入了绕日轨道
After leaving Earth, Starman ended up on an orbit around the sun.
Starman回到地球的可能已经微乎其微了
The chances of Starman coming back to Earth are extremely low.
它的轨道和地球下次相交要等到2047年
Its orbit isn't expected to intersect Earth until the year 2047.
即使那个时候到来 它也只会在距离地球200万公里的地方擦肩而过
Even when this happens, it will only pass by briefly at a distance of 2 million miles.
短暂的相遇之后 它将继续绕太阳运行
After this close encounter, it will continue on its orbit around the sun,
下次相遇就又要再等几十年
not returning to Earth for at least another few decades.
纵观整个人类航天史 我们已经发射了上百个物体离开地球轨道
Throughout the history of spaceflight, we have launched hundreds of objects beyond Earth's orbit.
比如旅行者号探测器 已经可以加速到离开太阳系
Some objects like the Voyager space probes, have even gone fast enough to leave the solar system.
有些航天器一旦进入太空 可能就是永别
Once something is sent into space, that is usually the last goodbye.
除了某些设计就是可返回的航天器外
And unless something is specifically designed to return,
其他航天器基本余生都要在太空度过了
these objects are destined to spend the rest of their lives in space.
每天又有很多自然天体会进入地球大气层
Natural objects however enter Earth's atmosphere everyday.
绝大多数是太阳系很久以前大型陨石的碎片
Most of these are large fragments of asteroids that broke apart a long time ago in our Solar System.
有些能大到挺过再入地球大气阶段的高温
Some of these are large enough to survive the intense journey through Earth's atmosphere
并到达地球表面
and reach the surface.
回到2020年9月
Back in September of this year,
天文学家正在使用夏威夷毛伊岛NASA的望远镜调查这些陨石
astronomers were observing some of these asteroids using the NASA survey telescope on the island of Maui.
该团队的天文学家主要观察飞向地球的陨石
This specific group of astronomers were focusing on asteroids heading in the direction of Earth.
他们发现了一个正在飞向地球物体 其数值有些异常
They discovered an object that was heading towards Earth with some unusual characteristics.
该物体以每小时3000公里的速度飞掠月球 比一般陨石的速度慢得多
This object flew past our Moon at 3,000km/h, much slower than the typical speed of an asteroid,
通常数值能到每小时上万公里
which can sometimes reach tens of thousands of km/h.
绝大多数陨石的轨道更加椭圆 且轨道平面和地球也相差很多
Most asteroids have a more oval-shaped orbit, on a plane that's tilted compared to Earth.
对该物体的初步计算发现 它的绕日轨道非常接近圆
Initial calculations of this object showed that it had a very circular orbit around the sun,
和地球很接近
similar to that of Earth.
进一步观测后 该物体的轨道面也几乎没有倾角
On further inspection, the orbital plane of this object wasn't tilted,
甚至是完美匹配地球的轨道倾角
and in fact perfectly matched the orbital plane of Earth.
这个轨道如此像地球轨道的物体让天文学家怀疑这可能根本不是一个陨石
This low velocity paired with an Earth-like orbit
made the astronomers think that this wasn't an asteroid,
而是一个从地球发射的人造物体
but in fact an artificial object that originated from Earth.
他们继续观测该物体 并把它命名为2020SO
They continued to observe this object and gave it the name 2020SO.
再进一步观测它的轨道并往回推算
After further analysis and tracing back its orbit,
他们发现2020SO的轨道在1966年和地球有一次近距离接触
they found that object 2020 made a close approach to Earth back in 1966.
翻看当年的发射记录
Looking through the launch archives from this time period,
他们发现了一次任务与计算结果高度重合：勘测者2号月球着陆器
they found a mission that lined up with this almost perfectly: the Surveyor 2 mission.
它由一枚Atlas-Centaur火箭发射升空并飞向月球
Lifting off from Cape Canaveral on an Atlas-Centaur rocket, Surveyor 2 headed for the Moon.
设计用于在月球表面进行一些实验 并传回月表的一些照片
It was designed to conduct experiments on the Lunar surface and send back detailed images
帮助NASA为未来阿波罗任务制定计划
which would help NASA plan for the upcoming Apollo missions.
毕竟当时离人类第一次等上月球只剩3年了
After all, humans were just 3 years away from walking on the Moon
但当时人类对即将要去的那个世界还知之甚少
and yet very little was known about the world they would be entering.
发射之后 Centaur上面级将月球着陆器送入奔月轨道
After launch, the Centaur upper stage placed the spacecraft on a path towards the Moon.
但当着陆器尝试调整轨道的时候
But as Surveyor tried to refine it's path,
它的一个推进器发生故障 导致着陆器失控
one of its thrusters failed and caused the spacecraft to lose control,
最终以接近每小时一万公里的速度撞月
until it hit the Moon at almost 10,000km/h.
而Centaur上面级则继续滑行
The Centaur upper stage continued on,
飞掠月球 进入一条未知的绕日轨道
flying past the Moon and entering into an unknown orbit around the sun.
数十年来 这枚上面级火箭就这样一圈圈绕着太阳飞
For decades, this rocket booster was out there doing laps around the sun.
它的轨道则持续受到太阳光压的影响
But it's orbit was slowly being changed by the continuous pressure from the sun.
太阳发出的辐射会对太空中的物体施加一个持续而很小的力
The radiation which blasts out from the Sun exerts a small but constant force on objects in space,
就像微风一样
like a very gentle breeze.
而Centaur上面级和一个空铁桶差不多
Since the Centaur booster is essentially an empty metal tube,
重量很轻 但表面积很大
it's very lightweight but still has a large surface area.
所以它比实心的重陨石更容易受到太阳风的影响
This makes it much more susceptible to the solar winds than a dense and heavy asteroid.
在注意到这种逐渐发生的轨道上的改变后
After observing this gradual change in orbit,
天文学家心中基本确认这绝逼不是陨石 肯定是人造物体
astronomers confirmed that this couldn't be an asteroid and it must be something made by humans.
但天文学家还是不能肯定它到底是不是
But the astronomers still weren't sure if this object really was
60年代发射的Centaur上面级火箭碰巧返回地球了
the Centaur rocket from the 60's making a surprise return to Earth.
2020SO会在11月进入地球轨道范围
2020 was on a trajectory to enter Earth's orbit in November
天文学家计算这段时间内它会和地球近距离飞跃几次
and the astronomers calculated that it would make several close approaches during its stay,
之后会在3月左右返回绕日轨道
before returning to an orbit around the Sun in March.
其间是最好的观测该物体
This would be a great chance to observe the object in more detail
并确认它到底是不是Centaur火箭的机会
and determine if it really was the Centaur rocket.
然而 该物体实在是太难观测了
However, this object was incredibly faint
需要地球上最强的那批望远镜才能观测到
and required some of the world's most powerful telescopes to even see it.
在它离我们最近的时候 星等会达到约14
At its closest approach, it would reach an apparent magnitude of just 14.
人类肉眼能看到6以下的星等
On the magnitude scale, objects only become visible to the human eye once they reach 6 or below.
直观来讲 太阳系绝大多数行星星等是低于1的
To put this into perspective, most of the planets in our solar system have a magnitude below 1
即使是它们裸眼看也还是挺费劲的
and even they can be difficult to spot with the naked eye.
科学家们唯一能证明它到底是不是Centaur火箭的办法
The only way the scientists could prove this was the Centaur rocket
是看它是否含有制造它的金属——301不锈钢
would be to find out if it was made from the same material, 301 stainless steel.
如何做到呢？科学家们拿NASA在夏威夷的红外望远镜
In order to do this, scientists took over NASA's infrared telescope in Hawaii
开始进行光谱观测
and began doing spectroscopy observations.
这架望远镜有3米直径主镜 且架在海拔四千米的高山上
This telescope has a 3 meter wide mirror and is located at an altitude of 4,000m on top of a mountain.
在红外波段有很宽的观测波段范围
It can measure a wide range of wavelengths in the infrared spectrum,
从而可以进行光谱观测
allowing it to perform spectroscopy observations.
这项技术通常用于研究太阳系以外行星的大气
This technique is often used to study the atmosphere of distant exoplanetes,
从而研究它们都由哪些元素构成
to determine what elements they are made of.
当行星在环绕的恒星前飞过时
As a planet passes in front of its star,
其大气层的分子会吸收特定波长的光
the molecules in the atmosphere absorb light at specific wavelengths.
通过观察这些在特定波长的吸收点
By observing these dips at specific wavelengths,
我们就能和地球上已有物质的数据进行对比
we can compare it to the data we have here on Earth
从而判断出大气中含有哪些原子和分子
and determine which atoms and molecules are present in the atmosphere.
同样的技术也可以用于判断某个固体的制造材料
The same technique can be used on a solid object to determine its material.
制造不锈钢的原子和分子会吸收特定波长的光
The atoms and molecules that make up stainless steel
will emit and absorb light at very specific wavelengths.
所以 科学家们对2020SO进行了光谱观测
So, the scientists took spectral measurements of object 2020
并与地球上的不锈钢的观测结果进行对比
and compared it to measurements made of stainless steel here on Earth.
经过对比后 科学家就能知道两者是否有相同的光谱特性
With this data, the scientists could compare the two measurements
and see if they had similar light behaviour.
数据的确有一些相似 但和完美匹配还差点意思
The data showed some similarities, but the match was far from perfect.
科学家意识到结果上的差异可能是因为地球上普通的不锈钢
They realized that the difference in results could have been from observing ordinary stainless steel
和在外太空恶劣条件暴露54年的不锈钢可能不一样
against stainless steel which had been exposed to the harsh conditions of outer space for 54 years.
为了找到类似条件的匹配对象 他们需要一个同样在太空飞了那么久的不锈钢
In order to get a real match, they would need to compare it to a piece of stainless steel
that has also seen the harshness of space.
幸好 1962年至今一共有245枚Centaur上面级火箭进入太空
Luckily, there have been 245 Centaur launches since 1962
很多古老的上面级还在地球轨道运行
and many of the old stages still remain in Earth's orbit.
但观察这些老火箭之一可能很难
But observing one of these old rocket stages for long enough would be a massive challenge.
地球轨道的物体在地面观测可能移动速度非常快
Objects in Earth's orbit can move across the sky at an incredible speed.
这意味着NASA的红外望远镜可能很难锁定物体足够久来获取足够数据
This means NASA's infrared telescope would struggle to lock onto the object
for long enough to get a good amount of data.
他们最终选择了一枚1971年发射的Centaur上面级火箭
They chose to observe a Centaur rocket stage which launched in 1971,
它曾把一颗通信卫星送入轨道
taking a communication satellite into orbit.
尽管难度不小 科学家们还是锁定观测了这枚49年前发射的火箭
Despite the challenge, the scientists managed to lock onto the 49 year old rocket
并获取了所有需要的数据
and gather all the data they needed.
在同一天 2020SO也在最近距离飞跃了地球
This happened on the same day that object 2020 made its closest approach to Earth.
数据传回后 这枚老火箭的光谱图和2020SO完美匹配
The data came back
and the spectrum graph of this old rocket stage perfectly matched that of object 2020.
证实了2020SO就是由301不锈钢制造的
This proved that object 2020 was made of 301 stainless steel
确认了它肯定就是1966年飞丢了的Centaur上面级
and was undoubtedly the lost Centaur booster from 1966.
随着我们往太空发射越来越多的物体
So as we continue to launch more and more objects into space,
我们探测那些飞向地球的物体的能力变得尤为重要
our ability to detect which objects are heading towards Earth will become increasingly important.
随着人类的脚步逐渐拓展向太空 随着人类的科技不断进步
As our presence in space increases and our technology becomes more advanced,
对这些物体的观测将渐渐趋于常规
observing objects like this will become much more routine.
对于2020SO 它将在3月飞离地球并继续环绕太阳
For object 2020, it will leave Earth's orbit in March and continue orbiting the sun
直到在遥远的未来某天再次和地球相遇
until it eventually returns to Earth again in the distant future.
像Starman一样 这些物体未来的旅程可能不是我们有限的人生能想象到的
Like Starman, these objects are on a journey that us humans could never imagine.
但根据物理定律 它们总会在未来某天回到初始的原点
But due to the laws of physics, they always end up coming home at some point.
当2020SO最终回到地球
When 2020 eventually returns to Earth again,
谁又能想到那时我们的科技会发展到什么程度 我们又会在太空做哪些事情？
who knows how far our technology will have advanced and what kind of things we will be doing in space.
想要继续漫游宇宙 我们要做的是继续培养下一代的科学家和工程师
But it's up to us to teach the next generation of scientists and engineers about the wonders of space.
那么有没有一款……
感谢观看本期视频 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.